<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: School | The Sweet Spot]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.g9labs.com/category/school/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.g9labs.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-19T16:14:47-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.g9labs.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Hao]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Designing the ThinkAnywhere Logo]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.g9labs.com/2008/04/07/designing-the-thinkanywhere-logo/"/>
    <updated>2008-04-07T10:33:04-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.g9labs.com/2008/04/07/designing-the-thinkanywhere-logo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my IEOR190A class (entrepreneurship), we&rsquo;re developing a business plan of a company making a device that tracks gestures on any surface. Install it on a whiteboard or a chalkboard and boom, your gesture strokes are digitized and recorded on any Bluetooth-enabled computer.</p>

<p>This device is actually implemented right now by our friend Leo Tran in one of his EE classes, using only an LED light and a Wiimote controller. It works by using the infrared camera within the Wiimote to recognize the movement of the LED. The Wiimote then broadcasts its data to a computer via its Bluetooth link.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.g9labs.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/04/thinkanywheresketches.jpg"><img src="http://blog.g9labs.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/04/thinkanywheresketches.jpg" alt="ThinkAnywhere Design Sketches" /></a></p>

<h5>Some concept sketches, just for fun.</h5>

<p>Now in designing the logo for this product, I wanted to convey a clean feel for the brand. Smooth, swooshy gradients and simple shapes tend to work well for this kind of thing. So I built a chalkboard (the green) and drew our device mounted above the chalkboard. The yellow beam conveys the idea that our device works via camera sensors.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.g9labs.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/04/thinkanywhere-icon.jpg"><img src="http://blog.g9labs.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/04/thinkanywhere-icon.jpg" alt="ThinkAnywhere Branding" /></a></p>

<h5>Voila.</h5>

<p>The logo was built entirely in Illustrator. I went with a dark background so the lighter shades of the camera, the IR beam and chalkboard could get a &ldquo;pop&rdquo;. The font you see there is Colaborate Bold&mdash;it&rsquo;s nicely <a href="http://www.smashingmagazine.com/2007/02/24/five-more-freefonts-chucara-preface-colaborate/">given out for free</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Noam Chomsky is The Man]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.g9labs.com/2008/02/17/noam-chomsky-is-the-man/"/>
    <updated>2008-02-17T15:53:54-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.g9labs.com/2008/02/17/noam-chomsky-is-the-man</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Why?</p>

<p>The man is a respected thinker, theorist and activist. I&rsquo;ve had several Mass Communications classes devote a couple of sections to his thoughts about mass media and its effect in forming dissent and complacency in the masses.</p>

<p>The man took a period of his life in the 50&rsquo;s devoted to formalizing computer languages (he is by profession, a linguist). We just went over <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chomsky_normal_form">Chomsky normal form</a> in my CS164 (compilers) course&mdash;a recursive method for generating languages from a set of rules.</p>

<p>My CS and humanities world collide, but this man has done it way before. How stunning. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noam_Chomsky">Noam Chomsky</a> is The Man.</p>

<p>(Disclaimer: I don&rsquo;t agree with very many of his views, but the purpose of this post is to point out that Mr. Chomsky is a man who&rsquo;s pretty much Done It All).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
